Guide to the Rhode Island Artillery, 5th Regiment, Company G. Records, 1861-1880 MS 253
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rhode Island Artillery, 5th Regiment, Company G. Records
1861-1880
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
United States. Army. Rhode Island Heavy Artillery Regiment, 5th (1863-1865)
MS 253
1.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Records of the Rhode Island Artillery, 5th Regiment, Company G., dated 1863-1865, including general orders, correspondence, invoices of clothing and other equipment, quartermaster store receipts, and muster rolls. Also includes papers related to the career of Capt. John H. Robinson, dating 1861-1880.
Historical Note
Company G of the 5th Regiment, Rhode Island Artillery, served in the Union Army during the United States Civil War (1861-65), during which time its members were stationed for some time near New Berne, North Carolina. The records in this collection provide names of those serving in the Company, various types of equipment and clothing issued, and methods used for provisioning of supplies and tracking of expenditures.
Scope and Contents
The Rhode Island Artillery, 5th Regiment, Company G Records measure 1.5 linear feet and are arranged in one document case and one oversize map folder. The collection contains correspondence dating from 1861-1880, including Orders and Special Orders issued at New Berne, North Carolina; invoices and receipts of clothing and equipment; and papers of one Captain John H. Robinson, recording his muster into the First Regiment of the Rhode Island Detached Militia in April 1861 as a private, his rise to the rank of captain, and evidence of his activities as a civilian in 1873 and 1880.
Access Restriction
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Mrs. Janet Messer (dealer) and received October 27, 1960.
Index Terms
Subjects
American Civil War (United States: 1861-1865); Military
Document Types
corrrespondence
Places
United States
Subjects (Persons)
Robinson, John H.
Subjects (Corporations)
United States. Army. Rhode Island Heavy Artillery Regiment, 5th (1863-1865)
- Series I: Orders, 1863-1865, 16237
  - General Orders, 1863-65, 16239 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Special Orders, 1863-65, 16238 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Invoices and receipts, 1863-1865, 16227
  - Invoices of Clothing, Camp, and Garrison Equipage Turned Over, 1863-65, 16236 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Monthly and Quarterly Returns of Clothing, Camp, and Garrison Equipage, 1863-65, 16235 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Quartermaster Stores Receipts, 1863-65, 16234 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Monthly Returns of Quartermaster Stores, 1863-65, 16233 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Invoices, Ordnance and Ordnance Stores Turned Over, 1863-65, 16232 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ordnance Receipts for Issue, 1863-65, 16231 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Quarterly Returns of Ordnance and Ordnance Stores, 1863-64, 16230 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Quarterly Returns of Ordnance and Ordnance Stores, 1864-65, 16229 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ordnance Expenditures and Unserviceable Ordnance, 1863-65, 16228 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1861-1880, 16222
  - Correspondence, 1863-65, 16226 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with Quartermaster General's Office (indicating receipt of reports), 1864-65, 16225 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence with Ordnance Office, 1864-65, 16224 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Papers of Capt. John H. Robinson, 1861-1880, 16223 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Clothing and ephemera, 16220
  - Clothing Rolls, 1863-64, containing name and rank or specialty of soldier, items issued, and signatures of recipient and witness., 16221 (Box Map dr, Folder 34)